Hey team, how's it going? I'm Corey and I go by Corey J.A. online and thanks for joining me for another episode of CoreyJA.fm, my solo podcast where I talk about what I've been building and what's been on my mind in the last couple of weeks.
And today we're gonna talk about, you know, something that's been on everyone's mind, I think recently, and that's AI and AI coding specifically and how I think AI agents might change how we work, at least in software and maybe a little more broadly.
And the title that I've been working on for this episode is that you should lean into the latency. so what I want to talk about is how I think AI agents are changing the shape of work, or least changing the shape of how I work.
And I think that there's a direction the industry can move in to really take advantage of this best. And really, the core premise there is that Latency is kind of the feature of these workflows and not a bug that we should try to replace.
So I think that agent workflows and AI have kind of started in a place of trying to bolt on to existing workflows.
I think the easy example is AI autocomplete encoding. The first useful, first really good use cases of AI encoding were autocomplete, like just completing the line, maybe completing the function, something like that.
needed to be really fast, right? Because you're in the editor, you're typing. It needs to be faster than you typing, or else there's no benefit, right? And so it needs to be fast, it needs to be low latency.
And I think that is a very natural place to start, right? It fits into existing workflows. You don't have to design new workflows.
It augments existing workflows and helps people be more productive. So I think that's a really natural first step. But I don't think it's where we will end up with AI tools and AI agent workflows.
And I think where we'll land is something a lot more asynchy, right? And I think the latency is really the determining factor here.
Agent workflows have a high latency by nature, right? Like, you know, they do two calls, they go back, you know, I'll kick off something and come back 30 minutes, an hour two hours later and see the result.
It doesn't fit the workflow nicely to like sit there and watch it. Like I can, I've done it before, right? Like I can watch my agents go and do work and it's fun. And you know, I definitely do that on occasion.
But I don't think that's the workflow we should be designing for. I think the workflow we should design for is a lot more async and like maybe more things in parallel.
And that gets into some discussions that I've been having on the internet around like, you know, context switching and how big of a drain that is. And I do want to explore those a bit, but like not today.
They're not my area of expertise. And so, I don't think I want to talk about the downsides of that too much. But I do think that if we can get over some of these downsides, or there are individuals, I think, who have more of a natural knack or training for this, working on multiple things at once, not losing the context in their heads, I think that kind of thing is a skill that might be more and more useful as AI agents become more popular.
And I think that one reason that fighting the async nature here isn't the path forward really is because it's expensive and technically hard.
Like Claude code, for instance, the coding assistant that I use most has fast mode. It has a low latency mode. It's just a lot more expensive.
And I imagine technically it's harder to pull that off. And there are definitely people and industries who can afford that and want that speed and can integrate it into existing workflows that way.
But I don't think that's the way that the whole industry should be behaving, right? We as an industry, like not everyone has millions and billions of dollars to dump into this, right?
And so I think one big way to not need to invest all that money and capital upfront is to lean into the async nature and be able to use not fast mode, normal modes, or even local models, right?
That are maybe slower running on your consumer hardware. But it's okay that they're slow, right? Cause you're not sitting there watching. You're just like, you know, starting it off and then coming back to check out the results later.
And I think that's really the way forward, right? And so I think that means though that as software engineers and people developing these workflows, either on purpose, right?
So we're building software that embeds these workflows or just naturally like how we use the thing, we kind of establish our own workflows, right? I think one thing that I'm going to try to be more cognizant of, and I think the industry might be moving towards in general, is designing around the async handoffs instead.
So acknowledging that async agent work is kind of the norm instead of the side quests.
Things are going to be async. That's the design constraints we need to design around to make these workflows really work and take advantage of them as most we can.
And so I said that copilot and inline editing was kind of where software development started. And I think that's like, kind of very true for all the software engineers that I know, right?
That's the first taste of this AI world that we got was Copilot or one of those other autocompletes. But now, to be honest, I think I have the autocompletes turned on, but they're not the primary way I interact with AI agents anymore.
And I almost forget that it's a feature because my workflow is very much agent async, where I will hand off a task to an agent.
get a PR back, or maybe I get a markdown plan back that I review, and then we implement. But it's very much hand off a task, let the agent go for a bit, it creates an artifact, I come back and review it, and then we do the same thing again.
I review it, we make a new artifact, whether that's a new plan, or maybe we approve the plan and write code. But it's very async. Here's a task, and then come back to me when it's done, and I'll review it type of thing.
And I think this is very different than a synchronous pair programming session, where you're working with another human or even another agent live, asking questions, working through things together.
I think there's benefits of both, right? But they're very different paradigms. And I think in general, as an industry, we should acknowledge that they're different and maybe start to acknowledge that the async one is more natural for AIs rather than the synchronous one.
And I think that's very different. I think synchronous workflows have been kind of the bread and butter. for software engineers, at least in general, for a long time. We always talk about context switching and optimizing for flow state and things like that.
And I think with AI agents, it might be the first time where some of that might change. I don't think all of it will, though. And I think that's the next thing I really want to talk about is that I don't think this context switching works for all tasks.
And I think maybe this gets into some of the discussion that I've seen on the internet this last week about it. about how context switching, like, you know, the normal things.
When you context switch, you lose all the context, and it takes longer to get reacquainted with that context than it would have just to not lose it in the first place.
And I think that's very true. And I think it depends on the type of work. In Moll, my agent software stack that I use for software development, I've found that there are types of tasks that I really go full Moll.
Like, they're totally async. I kick off an agent. It comes back with a plan. I review it and then we implement. Great. Super async. Love it. There are definitely tasks though where I've resisted going in that async direction.
I mean, I think it's been really good or I've not resisted it, gone in the async direction and still not liked the results. And I think with reading some of the stuff that people are talking about recently, what I've realized is that it's the creative work that really wants that synchronous flow.
And the creative work is a lot of different things in software engineering, right? I think when I say creative work to maybe non-software people, they think of the UIs, right?
The arty things, the things that like feel creative to everyone. I mean, yeah, definitely. Like if I'm doing some UI work and I want to make a component, I usually go synchronous and we work back and forth.
I get Claude to make me screenshots and I review them and like it's a much more synchronous process because I'm trying to like, you know, figure out, I don't know what I want yet, I think.
I think that's part of it. When I'm doing these creative exploration-y type works, I don't know what the end result is to ask for yet. And so I'm modeling the problem space with the agent in real time, a lot more like pair programming naturally.
But this only really fits me personally, at least, for these creative tasks, exploration-y tasks, where I don't know what the end result is.
And sometimes the- That's just exploration and there's no end result, right? Like the creative exploration work is just exploring, figuring out what works, trying a few things, seeing what doesn't work.
And then once you know kind of the shape of the problem and how you want it to fit together, then I've actually been moving to the async flow, right? So I use the creative synchronous flow to figure out the shape of the problem, but then I don't like do an implementation there, right?
And maybe we scaffold some things, maybe we test some versions out. But I throw them away usually, and then I start with the async flow again. And maybe I didn't need to throw it away, like case by case things, I think, specifically there.
But I do really think using synchronous work for creative exploration, and then once you can get a handle on the problem, that's when it's time to come back to this async workflow that agents are really native to.
And so I think with all that said, I think there are maybe some new skills that are becoming more more relevant with agent work.
And these aren't skills that weren't relevant before, right? It's just maybe skills that were relevant to a slightly different role than software engineering. A lot of them are slightly more product management-y and things like that, right?
And I think as engineers, we might all be moving more into that role, unless the keyboard monkey type role. And I think that'll be interesting, right?
I think it's a very big change for everyone in the industry. And I'm excited to see how we can navigate it, but it's not going to be. know, the same, everything's changing up on us a little bit. And so I think that context switching is a thing that might become a more necessary skill for software engineering.
And I'm wondering if people who resist it or haven't trained in context switching might struggle a little bit at first, especially because it's such a big change from their normal workflow.
And along with being able to context switch more efficiently, I think there's things like knowing when to trade off from that exploration work. to the grounded async work.
So figuring out when to decompose work, when you have enough of a sense of the problem that it makes sense to break it down. And then how you break it down. Because I've been doing these AI agent things for a long time.
And I think, like lots of us, I've gone on different swings where I'm just like, hey, build me an app. And then all the way to, OK, make the button red as a single task.
And trying to find that balance in the middle and how you decompose the problems, I think, is going to be a much bigger skill. And I think that's a skill that's already been necessary, right?
But maybe for a slightly different role than the software engineer again, I think of this as like a project planning type rule, right? Figuring out how to slice up the tasks, make vertical slices, that kind of thing.
I think that's a skill that's always existed in software engineering, right? But it might not have been one that was always thought of as the actual software engineering process. I think it always was, right?
But it's just how we think about these things. And so I think those are gonna be skills that are gonna get more and more popular and more and more necessary as we switch to this agentic world.
And so I think we've been talking a lot about the skills of the software engineer and like, you know, how that's going to change. But I think the other thing that's going to change is that with the move to async, like there's an orchestration problem here, right?
Just be like, you can sure set an agent off to go and do some stuff, but I think there's a lot of infrastructure and orchestration there that can really make it a complete experience and like actually help the workflows.
I think there's a chance that when people don't get the workflow today, it's because they don't have this orchestration, right? They're just putting it in cloud code, typing something, and then walking away, which I think is an amazing place to start here, right?
But I think there's orchestration that we're going to start building up in our tools here to help with these async things. And so the most basic one is when I send an agent off to go do something that I know is going to take a while, I want to be notified when it's done, right?
I don't want to have to keep checking on it and seeing if it's done. I want a notification. And so. I think things like that are going to be much more important, right? So get a notification when things are done.
But maybe that one agent wasn't the full pipeline, right? So like in mole, for instance, once a plan's done, a next agent kicks off to critique the plan and try to review it on its own first.
so chaining these agents together in interesting ways and orchestrating them, I think is going to be really interesting. But the thing that I want to dig into here is how those orchestration problems really tie back to the software engineer or the person using the agents, right?
So I think it's really about the async nature that makes it hard. In synchronous, you're there, you're reading it the whole time, you don't need to know when it's done, you're there, and the workflow is just more natural.
I think with async, we need things like notifications, and we need things like a way to snooze. Like, I get a notification that something's done when I'm at dinner, how do I remember it after dinner?
I don't want to just keep getting notifications every 10 minutes, right? Because then I get notification fatigue, and that's a real problem. So I think by moving to async, I think that's the right direction to go.
But I think there's a lot of stuff that we need to do to get us there, to be able to actually build systems that really allow the humans to drive the process, make the decisions, but the agents to do the grunt work and heavy lifting and have a real collaborative experience.
So there's hard questions to answer here. How do you give the agents enough context, but not too much context, right? How do you make sure the agents know when there's a human that needs to make a decision?
What happens if like during the middle of an implementation, an important question comes up that's not answered anywhere? Should the agent guess? Should it ask you? How does it tell you later that it made this decision up that wasn't part of the plan?
Do you have parallel agents? How do you keep them from clying? Do they collaborate? Is there a queue of tasks?
Is it one at a time? Where is this running? Is it running on your machine? Is it running in the cloud? There's so many problems. This is such a big problem space, I think.
And I think we're just beginning to explore it. have Cloud Code is the big handler, but we have open source handlers like OpenCode and Py. And I think those handlers will be the basic building blocks of this next layer of orchestration stuff.
And now maybe these handlers will build it in. But I think what we have today in the handlers is what's going to be the building blocks, right? We will orchestrate them in different ways, pipe them together in different ways.
Maybe you pipe open code and Py and Cloud code together for different use cases. Maybe each handler is not general like they are today, right? They're all pretty general.
They do everything. But maybe we get domain-specific handlers and things like that. And I don't think anyone knows the right answer yet. I think we're all exploring and seeing what's out there.
And I think that's awesome. think that's thing I'm most excited for here is exploring all these different workflows, figuring out what works and what doesn't. Maybe my mole autopilot doesn't actually end up working out and that's fine.
I'm having a lot of fun exploring and seeing what works. And I don't wanna talk too much about things outside of software. I think that's a very big trope right now.
I'm a software engineer through and through. I'm not gonna pretend like I can really speak to other industries. But I wouldn't be that surprised if this async workflow is one of the things that can unlock new use cases for other industries as well.
I don't know, we'll see. Maybe it is just software, maybe our text only and unit tests and lints and all the things we've built up over the last 40 years to really help ourselves.
Maybe that's what makes agents have the secret sauce in software. I'm willing to say that's distinct possibility, but I'm not convinced it's 100 % the case, right?
I think there's a chance that if we design new workflows for different industries that are more async heavy, there's a chance other people can get just as much or close to as much benefit.
as software engineers can. And so I think that'll be really interesting to see how it all plays out. But I'm gonna focus on software because it's what I know, it's what I like building for.
And so it fits really well for me. And yeah, so I think the last thing I wanna touch on is something that I kinda touched on, but async's harder to build, right?
There's more UX to think about, there's more issues. One of the issues that I'm having right now is different bottlenecks.
So I have my agent who runs, looks at my task list, and make PRs for me. And now I've got like 25 PRs that need to review, right? In a synchronous world, that doesn't really happen as much, right?
I'm looking at the code while the agent's writing. And so even if I have to review it at the end, I have some context of what was going on. And I probably don't have 25.
Because why would I start one, watch it walk, and then leave it and do 25 more, right? That's just not a problem in the synchronous workflow. But in the async workflow, it's definitely becoming a problem for me.
There is code being written at a rate much faster than I am able to review it well. And so I think there are definitely some new problems that we're creating for ourselves in this async world.
But I also think there's lots that means that we can play with and explore the right way to work around these problems. I'm excited. I'm excited to see where the industry moves here.
I'm having a lot of fun playing with these different workflows and AI agents. And I'm excited to see where the industry moves in general. I think we're definitely going to see a shift from these existing tools, kind of the, you know, the first iterations of these AI experiences.
I think we're going to realize that the old workflows maybe don't fit as much anymore, right? We don't need to bolt things on to our existing workflows. We need to think about workflows from the ground up with these new agent and async workflows.
and I'm really excited to play around with it. If you have thoughts on this, please let me know, reach out. And if you haven't been doing super async flows, I really recommend you try.
Pick up a task this week, decompose it into a few smaller ones if you think it's necessary, hand it off to an agent, and then walk away. Go for a walk, work on another task, write some emails, go have dinner, do something.
And just try it, see it for a few times, see what feels different. Maybe you disagree with me. Maybe the context switches are killer for you. Maybe they're not.
But give it a try. Kick off five things like this. Come back. Look at the five results. And let me know what you think. Did it work out well for you? Do you think there's some merit in these async workflows?
Or are you going to keep doing synchronous workflows even with AI agents? I don't think anyone knows the answer yet. So I think it's fun to play around, experiment, and share the results with each other.
So I'm going to keep working on mole, working on these async workflows. I'm having a lot of fun here and I'm excited to see what you guys think and what you guys build as well. And so with that, I think I'm gonna close up here.
This was a fun chat about AI. I'd like to make it interactive though. So if you have thoughts, please do reach out and let me know. So to wrap up, I'll do a prediction. In one year, I think the winners of AI workflows, especially in coding, are going to embrace async, right?
I think we're going to move away from needing to watch your AI tools type out their answers and move to a world where they just produce results for us to review. So please try it out.
Let me know what you think. And I will be back in two weeks for another episode. Thanks for tuning in. And until next time, see you later, team.